Welcome to 37 Degrees, the deep dive designed to make you the most interesting person in any room.
Absolutely. And today we're doing something pretty cool.
We're doing a temporal jump. We're taking Ursula K. Le Guin's 1969 masterpiece,
The Left Hand of Darkness.
The true classic.
Pulling it right out of the Cold War era and dropping it smack bang into 2025.
Yeah. Our mission today is, well, it's the ultimate compare and contrast. We're not just
revisiting it.
No.
We want to see Le Guin's radical intentions back then think second wave feminism, Cold War,
everywhere.
Right.
And stack them up against how weirdly prophetic and, frankly, how deeply relevant the book feels
right now. You know, with gender fluidity, toxic masculinity, our whole digital world.
You really can't overstate it. This book, it wasn't just sci-fi. Not by a long shot.
No, it was more like an anthropological thought experiment.
Exactly. Disguise is a novel and it fundamentally altered the DNA
of the book.
It really was a seismic shift, literally speaking.
Okay, so let's unpack that original moment, 1969. What was it like?
Well, you have to remember, sci-fi was. It was a boys club. Very much so.
Oh, completely, rigidly so. The environment for women writers. Pretty hostile.
Hostile how?
Well, get this. In that same year, 1969, Le Guin published a short story in Playboy.
Wait, Playboy? Seriously?
Seriously.
And she had to use the initials UK Le Guin. Why? Specifically so readers wouldn't know she was a woman before they actually, you know, read it.
Wow. I hadn't realized it was quite that aggressive. The assumption was just ideas had to come from men.
Pretty much. Political ideas, tech ideas.
Yeah.
Which makes the book's immediate success even more staggering.
It wasn't just a minor success, was it?
No. Left Hand of Darkness didn't just win, it swept the big awards. First novel by a woman ever to grab both the Nebula in 69 and the Hugo in 70.
So she didn't just like join the party. She crashed it and rewrote the rules.
She reset the whole conversation.
Totally. And what's fascinating, I think, is why it hit so hard. It wasn't just plot. It was the depth, the academic rigor almost.
You're hitting on the anthropological DNA there. That is absolutely key.
Her father, right?
Yeah. Alfred Kroeber, a giant in cultural anthropology. She grew up immersed in that world, field study methods, the whole nine yards.
Ah, okay.
So that's where that incredibly detailed world building comes in.
Exactly. She wasn't about inventing faster spaceships. She was inventing believable, complex alien cultures, complete with their own folklore, myths, legends, even untranslatable words.
Which ties right into the philosophy, doesn't it? The Taoism.
Deeply. She studied Taoism, even translated the Tao Te Ching later. The whole structure of Gethen, the planet winter, it's built on that yin-yang idea, unity through opposites.
Light and dark.
The titled self.
The left hand of darkness. It's from a Gastinian poem or proverb. Light is the left hand of darkness and darkness the right hand of light. Two or one. It's all about synthesis.
Back then it looked like, well, completely different from the usual sci-fi, right? The whole white guy conquers the galaxy thing.
Which Legreen openly criticized. Her move was radical. Forget external conquests. Let's look at internal human nature, cultural understanding, the messy bits.
And that shift leads us straight into the core of it. The thought experiment, as she called it. The gender stuff.
Famously said, the book asks a question it doesn't give an answer. A question about human nature.
And the question being, what if gender just wasn't a thing for most people most of the time?
Exactly. The Gethenians are ambisexual. They're androgynous. Summer, she calls it, for like 24 days out of 26.
Only during that short heat period, Kemmer, do they become biologically male or female.
Right. And boom, that's where the controversy kicked off.
Right.
Weird.
I
Love
TRUE
now. That's where it gets truly prophetic. How so? Well, back then, arguing about pronouns for
fictional aliens, that was purely theoretical. Right. A literary debate. Yeah, pretty niche.
Comparing with today's social landscape, I mean, those nuances Le Guin grappled with,
they're literally everywhere now. Mainstream. Pronoun usage, non-binary identities. Exactly.
It's discussed on TikTok, in schools. We're so far beyond a simple binary view. And it makes
sense that young LGBTQ plus readers today apparently rate the book super highly, like an
8.5 out of 10. They see it almost as a guide. Wow. So even with its flaws, the male default,
maybe ignoring same sex stuff, it laid the groundwork. It absolutely built a scaffolding
for feminist sci-fi that came later, allowing those ideas to be pushed even further. It's not
just identity politics either, is it? The prophecy extends to tech. Oh, yeah. Let's talk
tech foresight. This is fascinating. The Ansible. Le Guin invents this device for instantaneous
interstellar communication. Get this, it operates without radio waves, without energy. Pure thought
experiment back then. History shows us that. Well, it's basically the internet, isn't it?
Okay, it's maybe galaxy-wide internet, but still, instant decentralized communication. It allows
for what she called a looser interstellar organization, not some rigid empire. Which
is kind of how the global internet works, right? It connects everything, but doesn't impose one
single control structure.
And the term Ansible itself was so perfect, other huge authors picked it up later. Neil Gaiman,
Orson Scott Card. Shows her influence right there, embedding itself in the genre's vocabulary.
But her foresight wasn't just hardware, it was political software too, or critique of nationalism.
Yeah. The book sets up this tension on Gethin between the two main nations,
Karhaid and Orgareen. Karhaid is sort of chaotic, decentralized, lots of ritual,
very indirect. And Orgareen is the opposite.
Bureaucratic, state-controlled, centralized. Claims it's a utopia, but it's actually pretty
sinister underneath.
That contrast, that political allegory feels incredibly relevant today, doesn't it?
Totally. Le Guin called patriotism and nationalism an element of fear and hatred.
Fast forward to 2025, rising populism, isolationism.
Karhaid's unpredictability kind of mirrors some modern regimes,
while Orgareen's surveillance state vibe, well...
It's chillingly accurate. That whole us versus them thing she critiqued,
is still very much alive.
Okay, let's pivot to maybe the most psychologically prophetic bit. The main character,
Genly A.
Oh, Genly. He arrives on Gethin basically embodying 1969 masculinity, right?
Rigid, emotionally buttoned up.
Very much the product of an era focused on military might,
control. And he just cannot deal with Estraven, his main contact, who's so much more fluid.
And that rigidity, that emotional constipation,
is exactly what we'd call toxic masculinity now.
Yeah.
He sees Estraven's shifts, the Gethinian emotional landscape, as inherently weak or untrustworthy.
But hold on, is she saying he's toxic? Or just that his Terran culture clashes hard with the
Gethinian ways? Is it a value judgment or just diff...
That's a good question. I think she's saying when that rigidity stops you connecting,
when it breeds misunderstanding, that's when it becomes destructive.
And we see the fallout today, right? In relationships. That kind of emotional
immaturity linked to old school gender roles, it leads to breakdowns. What is it,
70% of divorce?
70% of divorce is initiated by women, often citing emotional unavailability.
Genly AI is the poster boy for that. The guy who has to be completely broken down,
stripped bare on the ice cap before he can actually connect authentically.
Which brings us to Shivgrathor, that amazing, untranslatable Gethinian concept.
Genly, Mr. Western directness, just cannot get his head around it at first.
Yeah, Shivgrathor is an honor, but also prestige through being indirect,
hitting meanings, saving face. It's complicated.
It's all veiled suggestion, not blunt truth. Genly just sees it as annoying political games.
But think about it in a modern relationship context. All that indirection, playing games.
It's a massive red flag, right?
Totally. It's emotional unavailability dressed up as cultural nuance.
It's basically, well, it's like ghosting or being super guarded,
playing games instead of being straight.
So the lesson from the book, even for us today, is kind of be wary of that.
I think so.
Yeah.
Genly's rigid adherence to his own cultural norms keeps putting him in a position where he's not being a good guy.
His inability to trust Estraven, who's the master of Shivgrathor, almost gets them both killed.
So the takeaway for you listening in 2025 is maybe seek out the Estravens,
the ones willing to be vulnerable, honest, even if it's complicated.
Seek Estraven, not the emotionally closed off Genly.
Yeah.
Find the partner who can be fluid, make sacrifices, connect deeply.
That synthesis, the blend of hard reality and emotional depth, that's pure Taoism again, isn't it?
Exactly. Unity through opposites.
That's the engine. Life and death, masculine, feminine, light, dark.
Genly and Estraven only really connect, become whole, when they stop seeing each other as other,
when the mask's gender culture fall away.
And Le Guin's writing achieved that synthesis too.
Rejecting the standard linear plot was another revolution back then.
Oh yeah. The structure is brilliant. Layering Genly's sort of formal reports with
ancient Gethenian myths, folklore.
It's polyvical, fragmented. It feels really postmodern actually.
Yeah.
That layering makes the world feel so incredibly real, so anthropologically dense.
It wasn't just genre fiction. It was capital L literature.
Proved sci fi could handle complex narrative techniques, tricky concepts like
мshiftгрэður or Нүсүүүүүүүүүүү, that idea of ultimate resignation.
No wonder Harold Bloom put it in the Western canon. It was just acknowledging the obvious by then.
And the setting itself.
Yeah.
scarcity, isolation. How does that resonate now? Well, think about Gen Z's climate anxiety,
that feeling of living on a harsh planet that demands adaptation, interdependence, not conquest.
Gethin is that metaphor. So the conflict isn't really aliens, it's communication,
understanding the other, whether that's gender, culture, or just the environment itself.
Absolutely. The legacy is huge. Left Hand of Darkness inspired so many writers who came after
Atwood, Gaiman, you name it. It opened the door. Proved sci-fi could be a tool for serious
intellectual and social exploration. And when you look at that final journey,
Jen Lee and Estravan crossing the Gold War on ice, that's the heart of it.
Stripped bare, literally. Yeah. Forced to shed everything, culture,
clothes, language games, until all that's left is this raw shared vulnerability.
That's where the real connection happens. So the book leaves us with this massive
enduring question, doesn't it? Whether it's 1969 or 2025. If you stripped away all the noise,
the societal relativism, the societal relativism, the societal relativism,
the societal relativism, the societal relativism, the societal relativism, the societal relativism,
rules, the tech filters, the cultural baggage we've piled on.
What's left? What's the authentic core version of you that remains?
That self, maybe.
Stripped bare, ready for real connection.
That feels like the truth Le Guin was searching for.
And maybe a truth we're all still chasing today.
Definitely something to think about.
If you enjoyed this deep dive of 37 Degrees, please leave a comment.
Find us on all platforms as 37 Degrees, Facebook, Instagram, YouTube, and of course,
TikTok. More content awaits at www.37degrees.info.
Join us for the next episode of Reading Fever.